<!DOCTYPE html PUBLIC "-//W3C//DTD HTML 4.01//EN" "http://www.w3.org/TR/html4/strict.dtd">
<!--
 ~ Copyright (c) 2005-2011, WSO2 Inc. (http://www.wso2.org) All Rights Reserved.
 ~
 ~ WSO2 Inc. licenses this file to you under the Apache License,
 ~ Version 2.0 (the "License"); you may not use this file except
 ~ in compliance with the License.
 ~ You may obtain a copy of the License at
 ~
 ~    http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0
 ~
 ~ Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing,
 ~ software distributed under the License is distributed on an
 ~ "AS IS" BASIS, WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY
 ~ KIND, either express or implied.  See the License for the
 ~ specific language governing permissions and limitations
 ~ under the License.
 -->
<html>
<head>
    <meta content="text/html; charset=ISO-8859-1" http-equiv="content-type"/>
    <title>Registry Search - User Guide</title>
    <link href="../../admin/css/documentation.css" rel="stylesheet" type="text/css" media="all"/>
</head>

<body>                                                                                              
<h1>Registry Search</h1>

<h2>Search</h2>

    <p> All resources found in the registry, can be searched through this interface. Search could be
    refined by optionally providing, resource name, created date range, updated date range, tags,comments, association type,
    association destination, property name, property value and the content. To search for matches containing a specific
    pattern use the <strong>%</strong> symbol. The pattern matching can be used with the following fields "Resource name",
    "created by", "updated by" and "property value". Also the search supports the use of part of the user name in the "created by"
    and "updated by" fields. And also for the fields like Created data range,Updated range,Created user and Updated user
    the negation option is provided in order to search other than the provided criteria.</p>

    <p>To enter more than one term in tags, use comma (",") as the separator. To enter more than one
        term in keywords, use space (" ") as the separator.</p>

    <p><img src="images/main.png" width="777px"/></p>

    <p>Figure 1: Search Interface</p>

    <p>Created or Updated dates can be either entered in the format of MM/DD/YYYY or used the date
    picker user interface provided.</p>

    <p><img src="images/date.png" width="777px"/></p>

    <p>Figure 2: Date picker user interface</p>

    
<br/><br/>

<h3>Custom Search</h3>
<p>The custom search provides the user with the ability to customize the search interface for a given media type.
The search parameters for a given media type is configured by a user with admin privileges by creating a resource
with the name of the media type (for <strong>application/wsdl+xml</strong> the resource name should be <strong>application-wsdl-xml</strong>)
and declaring the parameters as properties. The search parameter name is given as the property name and the property value
describes whether this parameter should be included in the custom search.</p>

<p><img src="images/configuration.png" width="777px"/></p>
<p>Figure 3: Custom search configuration </p>

<p>The advanced search contains a field where the user can specify a media type. Upon selecting a media type,
    custom search form for that media type will be automatically loaded.
</p>

<p><img src="images/custom_search.png" width="777px"/></p>

<p>Figure 4: Custom search interface </p>

<h2>Saving a Search Filter</h2>
    <p>
        Search criteria can be saved as a filter using the interface shown in Figure 5.
    </p>

    <p><img src="images/save_filter.png" width="777px"/></p>

    <p>Figure 5: Save search filter user interface</p>

<br/><br/>

<h2>Loading a Search Filter</h2>
    <p>A saved search filter can be loaded by selecting the filter name in the drop-down list shown
    in Figure 6. Upon loading a search filter, search form fields are populated with previously saved values.
    </p>

    <p><img src="images/load_filter.png" width="777px"/></p>

    <p>Figure 6: Save search filter user interface</p>

<h2>Report generation for search results</h2>

    <p>In the search result page the user is able to generate a report which will include search results.The user is able to
    create reports in PDF,HTML or Excel.</p>
    <p><img src="images/reporting_crumb.png" width="550px" /></p>
    <p>Figure 7: Reporting options</p>

</body>
</html>
