<!--
  ~ Copyright 2008-2011 WSO2, Inc. (http://wso2.com)
  ~
  ~ Licensed under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the "License");
  ~ you may not use this file except in compliance with the License.
  ~ You may obtain a copy of the License at
  ~
  ~ http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0
  ~
  ~ Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
  ~ distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
  ~ WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
  ~ See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
  ~ limitations under the License.
  -->
<!DOCTYPE html PUBLIC "-//W3C//DTD HTML 4.01 Transitional//EN" "http://www.w3.org/TR/html4/loose.dtd">
<html>
<head>
    <meta http-equiv="content-type" content="text/html; charset=iso-8859-1"></meta>
    <title>User Store Management - User Guide</title>
    <link href="../../admin/css/documentation.css" rel="stylesheet" type="text/css" media="all" />
</head>

<body style="font-family: Times New Roman,Times,serif; font-size: 12pt;">
<h1>User Store Management</h1>
<p>This user guide describes various configuration and management options available with user store management.</p>

<p>The User Store Management component of the WSO2 Carbon facilitates the management
    and control of user store configuration. The key functionalities of this component includes:</p>
<ul>
    <li>Create Secondary User Stores</li>
    <li>Edit Secondary User Stores</li>
    <li>Enable/Disable User Stores</li>
    <li>Delete User Stores</li>
</ul>

<h2>Default View</h2>
<p>The default view of user store management feature will show a summary of the available user store definitions.</p>

<p><img alt="" src="../images/index-view.png"/></p>
<p>Figure 1: Summary of available user store definitions</p>
<p>The default view will be as above, until we define a secondary user store. To add a user store, we can go through
    'Add Secondary User Store'</p>

<h2>Selection</h2>
<p><img alt="" src="../images/selection.png"/></p>
<p>Figure 2: Select a preferred user store implementation</p>
<p>Here it provides a form to define a user store, using the available user store manager implementations. At first we
need to select the implementation class we are to use. By default identity server provides 4 such implementations</p>
<ol>
    <li>ReadWriteLDAPUserStoreManager</li>
    <li>ReadOnlyLDAPUserStoreManager</li>
    <li>ActiveDirectoryUserStoreManager</li>
    <li>JDBCUserStoreManager</li>
</ol>
<p>In addition to the above we can add our own custom user store managers too. We just have to write our custom user manager
implementing interface org.wso2.carbon.user.api.UserStoreManager and make it available in the server.
From the drop down menu select the required user store manager implementation. It will provide a form to fill as follows
according to the selected class</p>

<h2>Define</h2>
<p><img alt="" src="../images/definition.png"/></p>
<p>Figure 3: Property defining</p>
<p>A little description of what each property means is also given for the ease. Fill all the mandatory properties and optional
properties as you wish.</p>

<h2>Save</h2>
<p><img alt="" src="../images/save.png"/></p>
<p>Figure 4: Try to add the user store</p>
<p>At saving the user store it will provide a notification as above. This means you have given all the required properties
and identity server is in the process of adding this defined user store to the existing chain. Please not that this does
not mean user store is successfully added. We have to wait little and refresh the page to confirm it.</p>

<h2>Status</h2>
<p><img alt="" src="../images/status.png"/></p>
<p>Figure 5: Status after addition</p>
<p>At refresh after a moment summary view will show something similar to above, if user store addition is a success.
    Then we can use the provided links to edit,disable/enable the user store.</p>

</body>
</html>
