<!--
 ~ Copyright (c) 2005-2010, WSO2 Inc. (http://www.wso2.org) All Rights Reserved.
 ~
 ~ WSO2 Inc. licenses this file to you under the Apache License,
 ~ Version 2.0 (the "License"); you may not use this file except
 ~ in compliance with the License.
 ~ You may obtain a copy of the License at
 ~
 ~    http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0
 ~
 ~ Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing,
 ~ software distributed under the License is distributed on an
 ~ "AS IS" BASIS, WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY
 ~ KIND, either express or implied.  See the License for the
 ~ specific language governing permissions and limitations
 ~ under the License.
 -->
<!DOCTYPE HTML PUBLIC "-//W3C//DTD HTML 4.0 Transitional//EN">
<html>
<head>
    <meta http-equiv="content-type" content="text/html; charset=windows-1252"></meta>
    <title>Security for Web Service - User Guide</title>
    <link href="../../admin/css/documentation.css" rel="stylesheet" type="text/css" media="all"/>
</head>
<body>

<h1>Security for Web Services</h1>

<p> Web Services security, or to be more precise, SOAP message security, identifies and
    provides solutions for general computer security threats as well as threats unique
    to Web services. </p>

<p> WSO2 Carbon supports WS Security, WS-Policy and WS-Security Policy specifications.
    These specifications define a behavioral model for Web services. A requirement for
    one Web service may not be valid for another. Thus defining service-specific
    requirements might be necessary.</p>

<p> The WSO2 SOA platform provides important security features to your service. By default,
    the security features are disabled. You should explicitly enable the security feature.</p>

<h2>Adding Security Features</h2>

<p> Understanding the exact security requirements should be the first step you should take
    when planning to secure your Web services. For an example, you may have to consider what
    security aspects are important to your service, whether it is the integrity,
    confidentiality, or both. </p>

<ol>
    <li>In the navigator, under Manage/Services, click <strong>List</strong>.
        The <em><strong>Deployed Services</strong></em> page appears.
    </li>
    <li>Click on the service name for which you want to add
        security features. The <em><strong>Service Dashboard</strong></em>
        page appears.
    </li>
    <li>Click <strong>Security</strong> in the <strong>Quality
        of Service Configuration</strong> panel. The <em><strong>Security
        for the Service</strong></em> page appears.
    </li>
    <li>To enable security for the service, in the <strong>Enable
        Security? </strong> drop down list, click <strong>Yes.</strong></li>
    
    <p><img src="images/no_security.png" alt="Turning on Security" height="144" width="1018" border="1" style="border-color:darkgray"/></p>

    <p><em><strong>Figure 1:</strong> Enabling security</em></p>

    <p>A list of available security scenarios is displayed. In addition to that, an
       option is provided to select a custom security policy from Registry.</p>

    <p><img src="images/default_scenarios.png" alt="Selecting default security scenarios" height="624" width="998" border="1" style="border-color:darkgray"/></p>

    <p><em><strong>Figure 2:</strong> Selecting Default Security Scenarios</em></p>

    <p><img src="images/policy_from_registry.png" alt="Referring to a policy from Registry" height="114" width="993" border="1" style="border-color:darkgray"/></p>

    <p><em><strong>Figure 3:</strong> Referring to a policy from Registry</em></p>
    
    <li>To enable security for your service, either you can select a default security scenario
        from the 15 existing scenarios (as shown in Figure 2) or you can refer to a custom
        security policy which is stored in Configuration Registry or Governance Registry
        (as shown in Figure 3). After selecting the suitable option, click <strong>Next</strong>.
        The <em><strong>Activate Security</strong></em> page appears. You can configure the
        security features on this page. The configurations depend on your previous selections.

        <br/>

        If you have selected a default security scenario, this page will show you the user groups,
        key stores etc. according to the selected security scenario. But if you have referred to a
        custom security policy from Registry, this page will show all the options to select user
        groups and key stores and you have to select those according to your policy.

        <br/>
        <br/>

        <ul>
            <ul>
                <li>In a default scenario, if you have selected a policy that includes Username Token,
                    you will have the User Group panel to choose the users who are
                    allowed to access the service.

                    <p><img src="images/activate_security_user_groups.png" alt="Activate Security - User Groups" height="250" width="1012" border="1" style="border-color:darkgray"/></p>

                    <p><em><strong>Figure 4:</strong> Activate security - User Groups</em></p>
                </li>
            </ul>
        </ul>

        <ul>
            <ul>
                <li>In a default scenario, if you have selected a policy that requires signing or
                    encryption, Trusted Key Stores and Private Key Store panels appear.
                    Select the KeyStore (wso2carbon.jks) and the Private Key Store
                    (Only the wso2carbon.jks keystore is available by default).

                    <p><img src="images/activate_security_key_stores.png" alt="Activate Security - Selecting Key Stores" height="312" width="1011" border="1" style="border-color:darkgray"/></p>

                    <p><em><strong>Figure 5:</strong> Activate Security - Selecting Key Stores</em></p>
                </li>
            </ul>
        </ul>


        <ul>
            <ul>
                <li>
                    <p>
                        If you are applying security scenario 16 (Kerberos Token based security) you have to associate
                        your service with a service principal. Security scenario 16 is only applicable if you have a
                        <strong>"Key Distribution Center (KDC)"</strong> and an <strong>"Authentication Server
                        (AS)"</strong>
                        in your environment. Commonly you can find KDC and an AS in a LDAP Directory server.
                    </p>


                        2 configuration files are used to specify Kerberos related parameters. They are, <br/>
                        1. krb5.conf - Includes KDC server details, encryption/decryption algorithms etc ... <br/>
                        2. jaas.conf - Includes information relevant to authorization.


                    <p>Usually above files are located at {server installation directory}/repository/conf directory.</p>

                    <p>
                        After selecting scenario 16, you will be asked to fill information about service principal to
                        associate web service with. There you need to specify service principal name and service
                        principal password. Service principal must be already defined in the LDAP Directory server.
                    </p>

                    <p>
                        Following picture depicts this behavior,
                    </p>

                    <p><img src="images/kerberos_spn.png" alt="Activate Security - Kerberos security policy"
                            border="1" style="border-color:darkgray"/></p>

                    <p><em><strong>Figure 6:</strong> Activate Security - Kerberos security policy</em></p>
                </li>
            </ul>
        </ul>


        <ul>
            <ul>
                <li>When you have referred to a custom policy from Registry, you will be provided
                    with all possible options to select user groups, trusted key stores and private
                    key store. You can select only the needed options according to your custom
                    policy and ignore others. Even if you select unwanted stuff, those will not be
                    used at runtime.

                    <p><img src="images/activate_security_custom_policy.png" alt="Activate Security - Custom policies" height="423" width="1013" border="1" style="border-color:darkgray"/></p>

                    <p><em><strong>Figure 7:</strong> Activate Security - Custom policies</em></p>
                </li>
            </ul>
        </ul>


    </li>

    <li>Click <strong>Finish</strong>. You will see the message "Security Applied Successfully".
        And you will be redirected to the Service Dashboard.</li>

</ol>

<h2>Disabling Security Features</h2>

<p>This function is used to disable Security from a particular service.</p>

<ol>
    <li>In the navigator, under Manage/Service, click <strong>List</strong>.
        The <em><strong>Deployed Services</strong></em> page appears.
    </li>
    <li>Click on the service name from which you want to disable security.
        The <em><strong>Service Dashboard</strong></em> page appears.
    </li>
    <li>Click <strong>Security</strong> in the <strong>Quality of Service Configuration</strong>
        panel. The <em><strong>Security for Service</strong></em> page appears.
    </li>
    <li>To disable security from the service, in the <strong>Enable
        Security? </strong> drop down list, click <strong>No</strong> and confirm.</li>
    <li>You will see the message "Security Applied Successfully".</li>
</ol>

<p><strong>Note</strong>: All default security scenarios are described in the wizard.</p>
</body>
</html>
