<!DOCTYPE html PUBLIC "-//W3C//DTD HTML 4.01//EN" "http://www.w3.org/TR/html4/strict.dtd">
<!--
 ~ Copyright (c) 2005-2011, WSO2 Inc. (http://www.wso2.org) All Rights Reserved.
 ~
 ~ WSO2 Inc. licenses this file to you under the Apache License,
 ~ Version 2.0 (the "License"); you may not use this file except
 ~ in compliance with the License.
 ~ You may obtain a copy of the License at
 ~
 ~    http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0
 ~
 ~ Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing,
 ~ software distributed under the License is distributed on an
 ~ "AS IS" BASIS, WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY
 ~ KIND, either express or implied.  See the License for the
 ~ specific language governing permissions and limitations
 ~ under the License.
 -->
<html>
<head>
    <meta content="text/html; charset=ISO-8859-1" http-equiv="content-type"/>
  <title>Server Roles Management - User Guide</title>
  <link href="../../admin/css/documentation.css" rel="stylesheet" type="text/css" media="all" />
</head>

<body style="font-family: Times New Roman,Times,serif; font-size: 12pt;">
<h1>Server Roles Manager</h1>

<h2>Introduction</h2>

<p><strong>Server Roles Manager</strong> is a component to manage server roles property for
   WSO2Carbon based products. Read more about <a href="server-roles.html">
   <strong>Server Roles</strong></a>.</p>

<p>As carbon supports adding different product features into one product instance original concept
   of the server role property   being added into carbon.xml is hard to manage as users may have to
   manually modify the carbon.xml to include the server-roles related to the product feature they
   have added to a carbon product instance. As WSO2 Stratos and WSO2 Mars are introduced above
   action is not possible for a tenant since the tenant user is remote to the server instance.</p>

<p>To overcome those issues server role manager is introduced. Server role manager will store the
   both carbon.xml default product roles and user/tenant specified server roles in Configuration
   registry. So when a C-App is deploying in carbon the C-App deployer will check for afro-mentioned
   server roles from the registry instead of carbon.xml.</p>

<h2>How It Works</h2>

<p>You can access the server roles manager UI clicking '<strong>Configure -> Server Roles</strong>'
   or directly from <strong>https://&lt;host&gt;:&lt;port&gt;/carbon/roles-mgt/server-roles-mgt.jsp
    </strong>.

Server Roles Manager Displays all the server roles included in the current product instance in the
landing page.

<p><img alt="" src="../images/landingpage.jpg"/></p>
<p>Figure 1: Server Roles Manager Landing page.</p>

In server roles manager, server roles properties will be of two types, <strong>Default</strong> and
<strong>Custom</strong>. Default type will be all the server roles picked from that particular
product instance's carbon.xml and all other server roles added by the user will have type custom.
</p>

<h2>Functionality</h2>

<p>Server Roles Manager has two basic functionalities,</p>
	<ol>
		<li>Add Server Role</li>
		<p>You can add any textual name as a server role without special characters except
           underscore.</p>
		
		<p><img alt="" src="../images/add_server_role.jpg"/></p>
		<p>Figure 2: Add Server Role.</p>
		
		<p>Click the link '<strong>Add New Server Role</strong>' and a drop down menu will appear to
           give the new role name. Just enter the preferred server role name than click
            <strong>Add</strong>, and it will add the server role name.</p>
		
		<li>Remove Server Role</li>
		<p>Simply click the <strong>garbage/delete icon</strong>
           (<img alt="" src="../images/delete.gif"/>) at the right side of the any existing server
           role. It will prompt a <strong>confirmation dialog</strong> and once confirmed it will
           delete the server role.</p>
		
		<p><img alt="" src="../images/delete_server_role.jpg"/></p>
		<p>Figure 2: Remove Server Role.</p>
	
	<p><strong>Note: </strong>Here users can even delete a default server role. Once it is deleted
        when next time loading server role manager will not pick it up from the carbon.xml.</p>
	</ol>
</body>
</html>
