<!DOCTYPE html PUBLIC "-//W3C//DTD XHTML 1.0 Transitional//EN" "http://www.w3.org/TR/xhtml1/DTD/xhtml1-transitional.dtd">
<!--
 ~ Copyright (c) 2005-2010, WSO2 Inc. (http://www.wso2.org) All Rights Reserved.
 ~
 ~ WSO2 Inc. licenses this file to you under the Apache License,
 ~ Version 2.0 (the "License"); you may not use this file except
 ~ in compliance with the License.
 ~ You may obtain a copy of the License at
 ~
 ~    http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0
 ~
 ~ Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing,
 ~ software distributed under the License is distributed on an
 ~ "AS IS" BASIS, WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY
 ~ KIND, either express or implied.  See the License for the
 ~ specific language governing permissions and limitations
 ~ under the License.
 -->
<html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><head>
  <meta http-equiv="content-type" content="text/html; charset=iso-8859-1" />
  <title>View Flows - User Guide</title>
  <link href="../../admin/css/documentation.css" rel="stylesheet" type="text/css" media="all" />
  </head>
<body>

<div id="middle">
<h1>View Flows</h1>
The View Flows feature provides graphical and textual views of the globally
engaged handlers of the system at any point of time. 

<p>The modules use the handlers to engage in different message flows at
defined phases . There are four different message flows defined in the system
(explained in the following section). You can observe the handlers invoked in
each phase of each flow in real time. </p>

<p>For example, the Apache/Rampart module (the security module of the system)
defines the handlers in the security phase of each flow, which handles the
security aspects of the messages that are transferred through these flows. So
if the Rampart module is engaged, you will see the Apache/Rampart handlers in
the message flows in real time. </p>

<h2>User Interface</h2>
<ol>
  <li>In the navigator, under Monitor, click <strong>Flows</strong>. The
    <strong>Message Flows</strong> page appears.</li>
  <li>You can switch between the graphical view and the textual view by
    clicking <strong>Text View</strong> or <strong>Graphical View</strong> as
    applicable. The textual view provides the name and the fully qualified
    classes of all handlers within each and every phase. </li>
</ol>

<p style="margin-left: 40px;">There are four different flows defined in the system. </p>

<p style="margin-left: 40px;"><strong>In Flow :</strong> A correct message coming into the system.</p>

<p style="margin-left: 40px;"><strong>Out Flow :</strong> A correct message going out of the system.</p>

<p style="margin-left: 40px;"><strong>In Fault Flow :</strong> A faulty message coming into the
system.</p>

<p style="margin-left: 40px;"><strong>Out Fault Flow :</strong> A faulty message going out of the
system.</p>

<p>In each flow, a message passes through a set of phases to reach the
service. These phases vary according to the currently engaged modules within
the system. The interface displays the current phases in each and every flow
as shown in the following figure. </p>

<p><img alt="Global Phases" src="images/phases.png" height="574" width="1020"/>
</p>

<p>In the graphical view of the message flows, click the links to get a view
of the engaged handlers in each phase.</p>

<p>For example, the figure below shows the handlers engaged in the Addressing
phase at system start up. </p>

<p><img alt="Handlers of Addressing In Flow" src="images/handlers.png" height="182" width="1020"/>
</p>
</div>
</body></html>
